Inventory of the Personal Papers and Official Records from the International Military Tribunal for the Far East 1945-1948
University of Virginia, Arthur J. Morris Law Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
Inventory of the Personal Papers and Official Records from the International Military Tribunal for the Far East, 1945-1948
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
MSS 70-3
This collection consists of 113 boxes and 23 cartons.
This collection consists of Frank S. Tavenner's personal files (26 boxes) as well as his set of the official records (195 boxes) of the International Military Tribunal for the Far East (IMTFE), 1945- 1948.
Frank S. Tavenner
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Mrs. Tavenner donated the collection to the Law Library in 1971.
Biographical/Historical Information
Frank S. Tavenner, Jr. was born in Woodstock, Virginia in 1985. He took and A.B. degree at Roanoke College in 1916, an A.M. at Princeton University in 1917, and an LL.B at the University of Virginia in 1927, after which he began the practice of law in his home town. In 1933 Tavenner was appointed assistant U.S. attorney in the Western District of Virginia and in 1940, became U.S. attorney. Following World War II was assigned by the Department of the Army to be Counsel and later Acting Chief of Counsel, Prosecution section for the IMTFE from late 1945 to the end of the trial in 1948. From 1949 until the mid-1950's Tavenner was Chief of Counsel for the House Committee on Un-American Activities. He died in 1964.
Arrangement
Organization
Series I: The personal papers comprising the first 26 boxes cover the years 1946-1948 when Tavenner was counsel to the International Prosecution Section (IPS) of the IMTFE. During 1947, Tavenner was Acting Chief of Counsel, in the absence of Chief of Counsel, Joseph Keenan.
Subseries 1: Reports, memoranda, court documents, etc. Boxes 1-7 These files are arranged by month, and begin with documents compiled in late 1945 before Tavenner's arrival in Tokyo. The end in May 1948, with the conclusion of the trial. There are a variety of documents included within this group, but in particular, they include memoranda between prosecution counsel, letters, prepared reports, analyses of interrogations, court documents, arguments before the Tribunal, and miscellaneous material. The written reports and memoranda perhaps form the most interesting part of these papers are they give insight into the attitudes and approaches of the lawyers making up the IPS, particularly in 1947 when he was Acting Chief of Counsel during the absence of Joseph Keenan. International Prosecution Section Counsel were allotted subjects to research in an early point in the trial. Reference should be made to the memorandum dated 8 May 1946 concerning the division of work at that date. Revised presentation lists were drawn up as the trial progressed and as it became evident that the trial would take substantially longer than originally estimated. (See memoranda dated 28 June 1946 and 18 September 1946.) These materials almost entirely originated in the Legal Branch of the IPS, which there were four other branches. The prosecution case lasted from 4 June 1946 to 24 January 1947. The defense case began on 24 February 1947 and continued until 12 January 1948.
Sub-series 2: Materials on individual defendants. Boxes 8-9 Besides his other duties Travenner was given "overall charge of the preparation of the cases against individual defendants." (see Memorandum dated 4 December 1946 from Eugene Williams, Special Asst. to Chief of Counsel, to IPS Associate Counsel.) These materials include both dated and undated memoranda and reports. There are also lists of references made to the narrative summary of the record. Additional folders contain extracts from Kido's diary, with sections relating to each of the defendants; references to the narrative summary by name of defendant in reference to other defendants' cases; analyses of the defendants by the Russian division; rebuttal evidence of the prosecution and defense--order of proof.
Sub-series 3: IPS documents numbered 0-4095; complete. Boxes 10-12 The analyses of documentary evidence contained in Series II of the Tavenner collection should be studied in conjunction with these documents, together with the collection of exhibits and rejected documents which are also part of Series II.
Sub-series 4: Newsclippings. Box 13
Sub-series 5: Reports, memoranda, and miscellaneous materials relating to Japanese/German/Italian collaboration. Boxes 14-15 This is another phase for which Tavenner had special responsibility. The IPS counsel working with him were O. Hyde and W. McKinney. Apart from general notes, memoranda and reports, these materials include the prosecution case for this phase; seven volumes.
Sub-series 7: Material from the Nuremberg Trials (1945-1946). Box 19-21
Sub-series 8: Shipping, Trade, and Industry Reports. Box 22
Sub-series 9: Assorted maps used for reference purposes within the Legal Branch--China, Southeast Asia, and the Pacific. Box 23
Sub-series 10: Two boxes of miscellaneous materials, such as reports and/or summaries of proof for the prosecution's case, and a statement of Joseph Grew, former U.S. ambassador to Japan, in support of several of the defendants. Boxes 25-26
Series II: A near-complete set of official records of the Tribunal comprise the second series of this collection. Included are a nearly complete set of the transcript of the proceedings, a complete set of exhibits, a narrative summary of the record, several indexes, rejected documents, defense and prosecution summations, orders and rulings of the tribunal, and the judgment.
Arrangement
It is apparent that the collection is not in its original order probably due to the manner in which it was shipped to the United States at the conclusion of the trial. It has now been arranged as much as possible in chronological order, although many of the files contain undated reports and reference materials.
Contents List
- Personal Papers 1946-1948 (Box 1-26)
  - Reports, memoranda, court documents, etc.
    - General Memos, Reports 1945 (Box 1)
    - Indictment 1946 (Box 1)
    - General Memos, Reports 1946, 13 folders (Box 1-3)
    - General Memos, Reports 1947, 17 folders (Box 4-7)
    - General Memos, Reports 1948 (Box 4-6)
    - Memoranda on Saionji-Harada Memoirs 1947, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Materials on individual defendants
    - Files on Defendants 1946, 14 folders (Box 8-9)
    - Extracts from Kido's Diary 1946 (Box 8-9)
    - References in Narrative Summary (Box 8-9)
    - Analysis of Defendants (Russian Division) (Box 8-9)
  - IPS Documents numbered 0-4095; complete
    - Reports, Summaries I.P.S. Documents (Box 10)
    - I.P.S. Documents 0-4095, 7 folders (Box 10-12)
    - Unnumbered I.P.S. Documents (Box 10-12)
  - Newsclippings 1946-1948 (Box 13)
  - Reports, memoranda, and miscellaneous materials relating to Japanese/German/Italian collaboration
    - Japan, Germany, Italy Documents, Reports (Box 14)
    - Japan, Germany, Italy Collaboration, 8 folders (Box 14-15)
  - Printed material
    - Tokyo News; Economic News April 1947; August-December 1947; Jan. 1948; June 1948, 14 folders (Box 16-18)
  - Material from the Nuremberg Trials (1945-1946)
    - Nuremberg Memos, Reports 1945-1946 (Box 19)
    - Nuremberg Prosecution Addresses 1945-1946 (Box 19)
    - Nuremberg Rulings of Tribunal 1945-1946 (Box 19)
    - Nuremberg Prosecution Vols. I & II 1945-1946, 4 folders (Box 19-21)
    - Nuremberg Decision and Judgement 1945-1946 (Box 19-21)
  - Shipping, Trade, and Industry Reports, 3 folders (Box 22)
  - Maps, 2 folders (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous materials
    - Selected Analyses of Documentary Evidence, 3 folders (Box 24)
    - American/British Phase Summary Proof (Box 25)
    - Relations between Japan, USA, UK and Philippines (Box 25)
    - China Phase (Box 25)
    - Manchurian Phase (Box 25)
    - Miscellaneous: Prisoners of War (Box 25)
    - Prosecution analysis of defense docs (Box 25)
    - Defense Documents: Reports, Exhibits 1947 (Box 25)
    - Misc. Defense Documents: Memos, Reports (Box 25)
    - Hoshino Defense Materials 1946-1947 (Box 25)
    - Joseph Grew--statement 1946 Oct. (Box 25)
    - Printed Material: Nazi-Soviet Relations (Box 26)
    - Miscellaneous: Japanese Nationalism, Militarism (Box 26)
    - Printed material: Events leading to WWII (Box 26)
    - Printed Material: Criminal Conspiracy-Japanese War Trials (Box 26)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 26)
- Official Records of the Tribunal
  - Transcript of the Proceedings 29 April 1946-16 April 1948, pp. 1-48412 (107 vols.) (Volume 27-133)
  - Index of Defense Witnesses and Documents in Evidence and Partial General Index for the Defense case n.d., 1 vol. (Volume 134)
  - Narrative Summary of the Record with Referent Page Numbers n.d. (Box 135-141)
  - Rejected Documents Arranged Numerically by Document Number, Defense Following Prosecution n.d. (Box 142-154)
  - Exhibits, 1-3915 1946-1948 (Box 155-191)
    Chronological Order
  - "Decisions of Imperial Conferences, Liaison Conferences...as Found in the Prosecution's Evidence" 1947 June, 1 vol. (Box 192)
  - Analyses of Documentary Evidence: I.P.S. Documents 1-4090 1946 January 11-July 23 (Box 193-198)
    Numerical Order
  - Analyses of Documentary Evidence: Analyses of 40 I.D.S. Documents 1947 April 8-1948 January 29 (Box 193-198)
    Numerical
  - Motions and Proceedings in Chambers 1946-1947, 2 vols. (Box 199)
  - Defense Summations divided into sections by subject, such as Conspiracy, International Law, Japanese-American Negotiations, etc; defense attorney responsible for each section is noted. n.d. (Box 200-209)
  - Prosecution summation of Conspiracy, Summations re Each Defendant, and Prosecutions Reply to Defense Summation n.d. (Box 210-212)
  - Chronological Summary of Prosecution's Evidence covering 1928-1945; an appendix breaks down by page number information on each of the accused; 1 vol. 1928-1945, 1 vol. (Box 213)
  - Orders by the Tribunal n.d. (Box 214)
  - Rulings of the Tribunal, organized under such headings as Affidavits, Argument, Cross-Examination, Evidence, Objections, and Witnesses n.d. (Box 215)
  - Judgment of the IMTFE: majority, concurring and dissenting opinions. 1948 November (Box 216-221)